hey what's up guys my name is aeno
welcome to another video today we're
going to be talking about functions in
C++ what a midweek video Am I Dreaming
has Cho gone crazy maybe but that's not
the point I just want to say a huge
thank you for everyone who's enjoying
the series I'm really glad you guys are
enjoying this cuz it's been a real blast
to make if you want to show me how much
you appreciate my videos you can follow
me on Instagram Link in the description
below lately I've been really into
photography and it would mean the world
to me if you guys could follow me just
like pause this video right now and just
go and follow me anyway back to
functions so what exactly are functions
functions are basically blocks of code
that we write that are designed to
perform a specific task later when we
get to classes those blocks are called
Methods but when I say functions I'm
explicitly talking about something that
isn't part of a class it's pretty common
for us to split up functions to prevent
code duplication we don't want to be
writing the same code multiple times
because of course if we did apart from
copying and pasting a lot of code and
just ending up with this huge mess it
also means that if we decide to change
some codee we have to change it in all
of those places where we pasted the
original code and that's just going to
be a disaster to maintain so what we can
do instead is just write a nice little
function that does what we want it to
and then we can call it multiple times
in our code if we need to you can think
of functions as having an input and an
output although they don't necessarily
need to we can provide the function with
certain parameters and the function can
return a value for us so suppose that we
wanted to multiply two numbers together
and we wanted to write a function that
did that so the the first thing I'm
going to write here is something called
a return value that is this is the type
that this function would return since
we're multiplying two integers that of
course will result in an integer so our
return type is going to be int I'm going
to give the function a name in this case
multiply and it's going to take two
parameters these are actually the
numbers that we want to multiply
together I'll just call them A and B
I'll give the function a body and all
this is going to do is return a * B so
you can see that we've got a function
here that takes in two parameters both
integers and simply returns the product
of those two numbers we don't
necessarily have to provide parameters
for example I could just not provide any
parameters and return something like 5 *
8 this is still a function that returns
an integer but it is just not taking any
parameters we could also tell the
function that we don't want it to return
anything and we do that by writing void
as its return type void of course means
nothing so instead this could do
something like log the result to the
console so let's go back to our original
example here where we had int a and int
B and we returned the product of those
two integers so how do we call this
function well calling a function is
pretty simple let's go ahead and try and
print the result of a multiplication I'm
going to first of all make a variable
which holds this result so I'll type in
result equals multiply and we'll go with
three and two so what this is going to
do is call this multiply function with
these two parameters and then store the
return value that is this result of a *
B in this result integer we can then
output that result result to the console
let's hit F5 to run our program and
after it builds you can see that we get
six which of course is what 3 * 2 is so
let's kick this up a not suppose that I
want to do a bunch of multiplications
and I want to log all of them to the
console if I do something like that
without a function then it would look
pretty messy so for example I need to
repeat this code so let's go ahead and
copy and paste it a few times I'll call
this something like result 2 result 3
we'll do 8 * 5 90 * 45 and if I run my
program and oh hang on a minute why am I
getting the same value everywhere oh
look when I copied and pasted this code
I forgot to change the variable now you
may have thought that I did that by
accident but I actually did it on
purpose to prove something this actually
happens all the time people copy and
paste blocks of code and then forget to
change one minor detail and in certain
situations you might actually just run
your program and not even notice that
it's not working correctly Until It
Breaks somewhere down the line and yet
something like this can actually be
fixed really easily if you just create a
function for it so let's go ahead and
fix this by actually printing out result
2 and three if I run this we will get
our correct results which is great
however you can see that I'm actually
calling this multiple times and it's
just a little bit annoying like for
example further down the road if I
decide to replace this multiply function
by simply doing something like 8 * 5
look at this I have to replace it in
every single place 3 * 2 90 * 45 that's
I don't want to have to deal with that
so this multiplication and then logging
the result let's go ahead and make a
function for that it'll be void because
it's not really going to return anything
to us it's just going to perform what we
ask it to do we'll call this something
like multiply and log and then let's
take a look at which parameters we might
want so what actually changes between
these three blocks of code the values
that we actually multiply that's it so
those become the parameters for our
function what actually changes between
these blocks of code what needs to be
specified for this function to perform
its job let's go ahead and write in our
parameters so we're going to be taking
in two integers A and B you can really
call them anything you want but A and B
seems sensible we'll copy and paste one
of these blocks into this function this
looks pretty good of course I'll replace
three and two with our parameters so
that we're using the parameters we
specify into this function to perform
the multiplication against which will
cause a * B to get multiplied here and
then we're going to be logging our
result to the console so now instead of
doing this so many times all I have to
do is simply call multiply and log with
my parameters so 3 and two for example
and then we have 8 and five
and then we have 90 and
45 and that's it look at that I can get
rid of all of this code and this is what
we end up with a nice clean and easy to
read program if I launch my program you
can see that we get the correct values
here so this is a pretty simple example
but I think it's effective in
demonstrating that functions are really
really important you should be aiming to
split up your code into many many
functions however one thing that I want
to stress is don't go overboard you
don't need a function for absolutely
every line of code that's not going to
be good for anyone it's going to be hard
to maintain your code's going to look
messy and cluttered and it's actually
going to make your program slower every
time we call a function asterisk the
compiler generates a call instruction
what this basically means is that in a
running program in order for us to call
a function we need to create the entire
stack frame for the function meaning we
have to push things like the parameters
onto the stack we have to also push
something called a return address onto
the stack and then what we do is we
actually jump to a different part of our
binary in order to start executing the
instructions from our function and that
return value that we push we need to get
back to where we originally were before
we called the function so there's this
whole like jumping around memory in
order to execute function instructions
and all of that takes time so it slows
down our program now the reason I said
asterisk earlier was because this is all
assuming that the compiler decides to
keep our function as an actual function
and doesn't inline it we're going to
talk in- depth about inlining in a
future video so the reason I'm saying
all this is because you don't want to
just go ahead and create a function for
absolutely every line of code don't be
ridiculous about it it takes a little
bit of experience to realize what you
need a function for but basically if you
see yourself doing a common task
multiple times create a function for
that the primary point of functions is
to prevent code duplication we don't
want to just be copying and pasting code
everywhere now if we go back to our code
for just a second you might have noticed
something a little bit odd about this
main function it says that it return
value is int however the return keyword
is nowhere to be found and I'm obviously
not returning anything so if I specify a
return value do I actually need to
return something let's go ahead and try
and just do nothing in this multiply
function I'll hitr F7 to compile my file
look at this I'm getting an error
telling me that multiply must return a
value so do functions with a return type
actually need to return values the
answer is yes they do the main function
is actually a special function the main
function and only the main function is
exempt from this kind of must return a
value if you don't specify a return
value it will automatically assume that
you're returning so it will be identical
to if I had written this this is just a
feature of modern C and C++ versions
that lets you just keep your code a
little bit cleaner and just for fun know
that this must return a value thing is
actually something that only applies in
debug mode if we compile in release mode
here you'll see that we actually don't
get an error that's not to say that what
we're doing here is correct because if
we actually do capture that return value
and decide to do something we will get
undefined Behavior it's just that the
compiler won't actually yell at us
however in debug mode with certain debug
compilation Flags enabled we will get an
error which will just help us debug our
code because at no point should you be
writing a function that says it's going
to return something but doesn't Okay so
that's pretty much a basic introduction
to functions functions are really useful
I'm going to be writing a lot more of
them in the future every program is
built from a collection of functions so
this is really important stuff if you
don't think you fully understand how
functions work don't worry because
throughout this series we're going to be
writing so many functions that you're
just going to get used to it and the
best way to learn is of course to
practice practice we also commonly break
up functions into declarations and
definitions so declarations we usually
store in header files and then
definitions we write in Translation
units or CPP files soon I'm going to
make a whole video dedicated to header
files and we're going to cover function
declarations in header files in that
video but anyway guys I hope you enjoyed
this episode if you did please hit the
like button don't forget to follow me on
Twitter and Instagram and if you really
enjoyed this video and you want to see
drafts of future videos early as well as
discuss what actually goes into these
videos you can support on patreon link
will be in the description below but
until next time guys goodbye
[Music]